- Maria: You have to... this is so absurd.
You have to put something on your head.
Usually a rag over the head [laughs].
I swear.
- Lucía: What's going on in our heads?
[laughs].
Oysters.
- Maria: Missing a rag.
[Starting music] - Maria: Hello, guys, welcome.
Today we have a very special class.
It's going to be a real conversation with someone you already know, because they've been there before.
in the channel.
It's Lucía, from ErrequeELE.
On Lucía's channel, @ErrequeELE, you will find very cool and little Spanish videos.
common because she dares, with the foul Spanish that we use every day, and with
useful vocabulary that you definitely won't find in books.
He also has a podcast in which he talks about Spanish, culture and even anecdotes.
personal.
How are you, Lucia?
- Lucia: Hello, Maria.
Super happy to repeat this talk with you and your listeners.
- Maria: Me too, honestly, because I have a great time with you, so I always
It's a pleasure to chat.
On or off YouTube, it doesn't matter, I always enjoy chatting with you.
So it's great to be here together.
- Lucia: I say the same to you.
Same to you.
- Maria: Well, do you know what we're going to talk about?
I've told you before, haven't I?
- Lucia: Well, yes.
Yes, yes.
I have a cheat sheet here [laughs], a cheat sheet on the subject.
So yes, I'm ready.
More or less prepared.
Because I'm not an expert on this topic, but hey, I have some ideas.
- Maria: Well, nothing.
At the user level, as long as you know at the user level, everything is fine.
No problem.
And, well, of course, the first question that always has to be asked in these cases, to put into
context, is if you are superstitious.
- Lucia: Okay.
Not at all, not at all.
Not superstitious at all.
I don't know if that's good or bad, but nothing superstitious.
- Maria: You know that, when...
Because I also did this topic in class, as I told you, and when I was preparing it,
I thought, "I'm not superstitious at all."
And as I was preparing the class, I was researching things, I said "oh, I'll do this,
I do this; I mean, maybe I am superstitious."
So, my goal today is going to be to try and prove that you're at least a little bit superstitious.
Let's see if I can do it [laughs].
- Lucía: Okay, good luck [laughs].
- Maria: Or maybe you have been in the past, we don't know.
- Lucia: I'd say no, huh?
I would say no.
I'll tell you as I go along, but I'd say no.
- Maria: Don't you do any of the typical things to attract good luck or to
ward off bad luck?
Don't you have any of these rituals?
Nothing at all?
- Lucia: Nothing at all.
I've sometimes, as a joke, done that "knock on wood, knock on wood" thing.
- Maria: Ah...
- Lucia: I did it as a joke, but not thinking that I would be lucky or attract good luck.
good luck knocking on wood, huh?
And I have to say that I once bought a necklace (although I lost it, I don't know where)
is, after so much moving).
But I bought myself a horseshoe pendant.
And not because of good luck, but because I liked it, that's all.
- Maria: Ah, I mean, not out of superstition but out of fashion, as an accessory.
- Lucia: It was beautiful.
- Maria: Okay.
Never...?
For example, for example, the most typical things, right?
Have you never, for example, avoided the number thirteen?
Did you say "oh, the thirteenth...
plane 13..."?
- Lucia: No, actually...
Well, I'm going to tell you something that I love, it makes me laugh a lot.
I got married a few years ago...
Well, for reasons of going together to Chira, etc.; not a full-blown wedding, no,
It was something more like "I love you out of interest, Andrés", also love, of course, but above all
for the convenience of traveling together abroad, without problems, etc.
And then.
- Maria: Visas and all that, right?
- Lucía: Yes, exactly, for the visas, so that no one would be left stranded and would have to
that he's going to lose his job or something like that.
So...
both being Spanish, eh?
So, we made an appointment to get married at the courthouse and it was...
Well, they suggested we get married on a Friday, which was the day we were most interested in.
We, because at that time we were also working abroad, we were in England,
and then we had to come on purpose.
And they proposed to us to get married on Friday the 13th, which was the only nearby day that there was space.
[laughs].
And we said (well, I especially said) "damn, Friday the 13th, how funny, it makes me laugh a lot,
We're going to get married, we're going to get married on Friday the 13th." [laughs].
I swear.
- Maria: Ah!
I can't believe it!
Well, to be a little honest, the unlucky day, actually, in the culture
Spanish is not Friday.
Which is it?
- Lucía: Yes [laughs].
It's a Tuesday.
- Maria: It's Tuesday.
Would you have gotten married on a Tuesday the 13th too?
- Lucía: Perfectly, perfectly [laughs].
- Maria: Wow, so...
- Lucía: Now, it's true that Friday the 13th is more Anglo-Saxon, right? If I'm not mistaken.
But I believe that it is already established in the Spanish-speaking world as well.
luck, more or less, for all the foreign influence.
- Maria: Because of the series...
- Lucía: Yes, we have it in movies, series and stuff like that.
So, that's why it was so funny to me.
"Friday the 13th, how funny, we're getting married that day" [laughs].
And if it had been Tuesday the 13th, too.
- Maria: Well, you know we have this saying: "on Tuesday, neither get married nor embark."
So, in addition to the 13th, Tuesday itself is a day of bad luck.
You can't start anything important on a Tuesday, I'm supposed to.
So there would be a double somersault with all...
But there are people who really see it the other way around, who see it as something of good luck,
even, that they have turned Tuesdays the 13th into something completely opposite "today I'm going to have
good luck".
I know a couple of people like that who are like, "No, no, I love 13."
Yeah.
[Start advertising] I take this opportunity to tell you that you can join
to my membership, the online classroom, to learn Spanish.
There you will have explanations and grammar tasks my way, the way I like it: everything very
detailed, going to the weak points.
You'll learn real Spanish, with clips from series and interviews, and with expressions.
You will improve your listening with activities and, of course, you will be able to download the documents.
to continue learning outside the platform.
[End of commercial] - Maria: I don't know, I want...
Now I'm starting to think you're not really superstitious at all, because, I don't know, those are
like the classics, like the usual.
- Lucia: Yes.
- Maria: But well, I don't know, maybe you have superstitious people around you,
although you?
Do you live or have you lived with superstitious people?
- Lucia: Yes, yes, of course.
I have friends who are very superstitious.
And, in fact, I have lived with very superstitious people during university, when it was necessary
hand in some work, or we had some exam or something.
Well, if an exam fell on a Tuesday, it was like absolute drama.
Or if I had a job done and had to hand it in "no way, today is Tuesday,
I'm not going to give it to him today, no way" [laughs].
Yeah.
- Maria: Okay, my goodness.
No, no, I can't go that far, okay?
I am a little superstitious about some things, but I don't think I've gotten that far.
never.
I have done that, for example, of...
In college, I had my lucky pen.
I had my lucky pen.
It's just that I always took exams with that pen, always.
Well, of course, it was over, but I bought another one just like it.
It always had to be blue or black, from the BIC brand, which is the cheapest brand that
good
But, I don't know why, I came to the conclusion that that pen was for me.
It brought luck for exams.
And I was much more relaxed if I had one of that brand.
Don't ask me why, it's superstition.
- Lucía: Ah, well that's very funny to me.
I love that anecdote, because the exact opposite happened to me.
It was a disaster.
I have come to go...
I mean, I was prepared for the exams, right?
I've always been...
Not a swot, but I do prepare myself enough to get a good result.
And what I was really terrible at was arriving at the exam with the exam instruments.
I have come to exams without pens.
I had to buy pens when I arrived at the exam (thank goodness, I always had some
(in advance) because I forgot.
So, I had to buy it or I had to ask someone.
In fact, in one of the last exams of the course, I had to ask, and then
I never met that girl who lent me the pen again [laughs], and I never gave it to her.
I was able to return.
And then in a master's degree too.
A master's degree in which I didn't know anyone, because it was remote, I also had to
leave a pen and I couldn't return it either.
Well, I'm a mess, so...
- Maria: No, but those things happen.
I mean, I think it's happened to me too.
Or to carry and, perhaps, the pen at that moment doesn't work or just runs out,
or whatever.
It's okay, nothing happens, in that case I wouldn't die like "oh no, now I'm going to fail"
because I don't have my..."
- Lucia: [laughs].
- Maria: It wasn't that, but it was like "come on, this helps me to be a little calmer, so
that's it".
Like, you know, consciously deceiving yourself that you know it doesn't make much sense.
but you still do it because it gives you a certain peace of mind.
So, well, there he went.
Anything that helps is good.
- Lucia: Yes, yes, in fact...
In fact, they are like manias, aren't they?
In fact, we see that in many athletes.
- Maria: Yes.
- Lucía: I'm not much into following sports, but for example Nadal who always has his
gestures, which he does when he is about to start playing, like a good luck ritual.
- Maria: Yes...
How to place the bottles or, I don't know, do something with the right foot, enter maybe
on the track with the right foot.
I don't know if he does it, but I know that many footballers, for example, do that.
Always enter the field with your right foot for good luck.
So, well, they are little things that make you a little calmer, more secure, but
They can become a real problem if you accumulate too many.
In the end it looks very strange, like Nadal, who I think does less things now than before;
but before it was brutal.
It was like...
He was touching his face all the time...
- Lucia: Yes.
- Maria: I bounced the ball 4-5 times, I don't remember.
It was a sight to see that man before a serve.
So, then...
- Lucia: And you can't say that things went badly for him, so he has a well-founded excuse,
¿no?
- Maria: Ah, look.
Clara, that's exactly what I think validates itself, "since things went well for me today, well
So I'm going to repeat what I did today, which is surely what brought me
good luck, not preparation."
But of course, something that makes you feel safe is actually helping you too.
I mean, like that placebo effect, right? If you think something is going to help you, in the end
your security increases and helps you.
So, in the end, well, I don't know, there it is.
It's not real, but at the same time it has a real component.
Well, it's like...
- Lucia: Exactly, yes, yes.
In fact, I'll never forget, and even though it has nothing to do with good luck...
But what you said about the placebo effect, I will never forget...
I assume you've read Harry Potter, have you?
- Maria: Yes, yes.
- Lucia: It's mandatory.
When...
Well, and the movies too.
When Ron had to play something in the...
Yes, what's your name?
¿Quidditch?
I don't remember, I haven't checked it for many years.
- María: Quidditch.
Me too, actually, many.
- Lucia: But I had to play, and then Harry pretended that he had poured a potion on her.
in his drink that would give him the power to win, and he didn't actually put anything in it.
It was the placebo effect.
- Maria: Exactly.
- Lucia: So, well, luck or not, repeating those rituals and all those things that make us
feel more secure, well look, if it helps us, what do we give it?
Even if it's a superstition.
- Maria: That's it.
Yes, even though we know we're deceiving ourselves, I trust it's important.
Okay, I have, I think, 4 superstitions that are, like, maybe exclusive to Spain.
I'm not quite sure.
But when I tell my students about it, they are usually quite surprised.
So, I want to check with you.
If you also know them, if it is something that is throughout Spain or that is regional, or
Maybe, not being a superstitious person, maybe you don't know them and maybe
Yes, they are known in Spain.
In any case, I'm going to tell you, I'm going to give you like superstition, and I want you to try
guess (or tell me, if you know) what happens in that case.
I have to look at my notes, my cheat sheet...
- Lucia: What's going on...
You got me there.
But okay, okay, let's try it [laughs].
- Maria: Of course, well, yes, yes, because what simply happens is that you have bad luck.
- Lucia: Oh, okay.
- Maria: But in some cases, bad luck is more specific.
For example, for example, what happens if someone sweeps your feet?
So, imagine you're sitting on the couch at home, and then...
Well, in your case it won't be possible to pass, but anyway, someone comes to your...
You live with your mother, or whatever, and she sweeps your feet.
When you sweep the house, you accidentally sweep your feet, what happens?
Do you know this supers...?
- Lucía: Does it have a negative consequence other than bad luck?
And apart from your feet getting covered in shit?
[laughs].
- Maria: Shitty [laughs].
- Lucia: Apart from that?
Don't tell me.
- Maria: Apart from that, it has a very specific consequence.
Does this not sound familiar to you?
- Lucia: Oh my...
No, but not at all, I mean, nothing, zero [laughs].
- Maria: Wow, now I'm even more curious.
Here it is said, a lot, "don't sweep my feet, I won't get married", because it is said
that if they sweep your feet...
You are a single person and they sweep you, they pass a broom over your feet, you are not going to get married,
you won't find a husband or wife.
That's why I said that in your case they can't do it anymore because you're already married.
- Lucia: Of course, absolutely.
The second husband [laughs].
- Maria: They can sweep your feet all they want, they're not going to take that away from you.
But a lot is said here.
Look, it's something, like everything, right?
Because it is true that superstitions in Spain had a lot of weight before, and now
They have less and less, right?
People aren't as superstitious as they used to be, but they used to be...
I don't know, maybe ask your mother, see if she knows him, I don't know, if it's something
generational, I don't know.
- Lucia: Yes, I'll ask my grandmother, because my mother...
Well, I was going to say "my mother is like me," but actually I am like my mother.
- Maria: Of course, yes.
- Lucia: Not at all superstitious.
So, I'll ask my grandmother, see if that sounds familiar to her.
- Maria: Well, I don't know.
- Lucia: You left me dead, huh?
I didn't expect it.
- Maria: [laughs] Well, I have more, I have more, because...
- Lucia: Okay, go for it.
- Maria: Well, this one I'm going to tell you I think is a little more normal, it's related
with the umbrellas.
Do you know this one?
What can't be done?
- Lucia: Oh, yes.
Sure, I know, it's bad luck.
Open an umbrella.
That you can't open an umbrella inside a room, but I don't know what the bad news is.
luck, death?
- Maria: I think it's just bad luck in general, bad luck.
I mean, I don't know...
- Lucia: Okay.
- Maria: In this case I don't have anything concrete.
I don't know exactly what's going on, unless it's raining...
- Lucía: You get me, I'm left wanting...
- Maria: Maybe we have a drought because many people have opened their umbrellas inside.
from home, I don't know [laughs].
- Lucía: [laughs] That's great, that would be great.
Yes, yes, it is a way.
- Maria: But not only inside the house, but even if it is a covered area (or
be it, like these arcades on the street).
My mother didn't let me open the umbrella there either.
My mother was superstitious, now I think less so.
- Lucia: That's great.
- Maria: And he told me, taking me to school he told me "don't open the... no, no, here already
close the umbrella because we are indoors", then we have to close the umbrella, it is
bad luck.
So, look...
- Lucia: Wow, look.
- Maria: You have no problem.
Would you open the umbrella inside the house?
- Lucia: No, no, no problem.
In fact...
But I know that it has happened to me that, within my family, I gave an umbrella to someone,
among other things, and we told him "open it to see it" and he said "no way, no" [laughs].
- Maria: [laughs] Exactly.
- Lucia: But of course, my mother and I were like, "Why don't you open it?
"I mean, you're not going to die."
- Maria: "We want to see the design," right?
But...
- Lucia: Yes, exactly.
- Maria: Well yes, that's it...
I think I will open it now, especially if I put it out to dry.
Well, it's just that this year it has rained so little that I haven't had to use an umbrella.
nothing...
But when that happens, or used to happen, I would open the umbrella on the terrace, which does have
a roof.
And there I open it and that's it, I don't care.
But inside the house it's like...
I always remember, I always hear my mother's voice "that's bad luck."
Actually, I think all the ones I have are because of my mother, because the next one that
I'm going to tell you it's also because of her.
- Lucia: Let's see.
- Maria: What happens if you put your bag on the floor?
- Lucía: Look, I don't do it because I'm very fussy and I don't want it to get dirty, but
I honestly didn't even know that this also brought bad luck according to superstitions,
that you're leaving me dead.
- Maria: Well, also...
- Lucia: What's up?
[laughs].
- Maria: According to this superstition, if you put your purse on the ground, the money will disappear.
- Lucia: Oysters, oysters.
Excellent.
- Maria: You lose money somehow.
That's superstition.
So, it's true that I don't put it now because...
for what you say, so that it doesn't get stained, so that they don't steal from me (maybe, that
It's the closest thing) [laughs].
- Lucía: [laughs] The money is gone, indeed.
- Maria: The money is gone...
Maybe that's what they meant.
We haven't understood it well, I don't know.
But yes, yes, my mother always says, "No, no, no, not the purse on the floor, or the money will go away."
And I was like, "Where are you going to go?"
- Lucia: How strong...
I want to meet your mother.
Greetings from here [laughs].
- María: [laughs] No, no, she's calmer now, but of course, every adolescence and
early years of adulthood, because they really sink in.
And the last one isn't from my mother, poor thing, no.
This is not my mother's.
The last one...
Dime.
- Lucía: Let's see, I'm going to be left wanting more, okay?
Because you told me it's the last one, but I'm delighted, I'm learning
a lot.
- Maria: [laughs] I told you they were curious.
The last one is not my mother's, it's my grandmother's.
It has to do with the sharpener.
This is the most curious of all.
Do you know who is a sharpener?
- Lucía: You say "sharpener" and I remember this man who... I suppose he looked
tan...
Well, I don't know, but maybe it didn't look that good.
This guy who drives the car is a "sharpener!", right?
- Maria: Exactly, that's correct.
Of course, in all of Spain, I think, we have this gentleman who now drives a car, but who
I didn't go by car before.
I used to ride a bike and I had the knife sharpener on the bike itself.
And there's a distinctive sound, right?
A little song, like a "shoot, shoot" [laughs].
- Lucía: A little music, but that mu...
Yes, yes, yes.
Exact.
[Music from the sharpener plays] - Maria: That's all over Spain.
- Lucia: Well...
Or in the south, because Murcia is in... I don't know, I don't know.
- Maria: Ah, well, yes.
No, but I've heard it from other people too, from other parts of Spain.
So the question is, do you know what happens when the sharpener passes?
There's also bad luck if the sharpener passes by and you don't do something.
- Lucia: And you don't do one thing?
- Maria: Yes.
- Lucía: You don't put down the knives [laughs].
- Maria: If you don't give it to him...
No [laughs].
- Lucia: Let's see...
- Maria: You have no idea, you have no idea, I know.
- Lucía: But I have no idea, I've never heard of it in my life [laughs].
That is, the gentleman comes to work, to sharpen your knives, and he himself can bring you
bad luck.
- Maria: You hear the music, and you have to do something.
- Lucia: Hum it?
Isn't it crossing yourself or anything like that?
¿No?
- Maria: No, no, no.
- Lucia: Oh, okay.
You have to...
This is so absurd, you need to put something on your head.
Usually a rag over the head [laughs].
I swear.
- Lucía: What's going on in our heads?
[Laughs].
Oysters.
- Maria: If you don't have a rag, anything will do.
I remember that I was...
When I was little, I used to stay with my grandmother and, of course, I used to go out with the neighbors...
- Lucía: [laughs] It's just that...
- Maria: Suddenly we heard the "tirurirí" of the sharpener and all the neighbors (I swear,
all of them), and my grandmother included, ran to look for something, a rag.
But if they couldn't find a rag, it was a magazine.
For example, these supermarket brochure magazines, for example.
And he gave me one.
My grandmother used to give me one to wear on my head.
And I was maybe 5 years old, with the magazine in my head saying "what's going on?
"Why are we doing this?"
- Lucia: I can't believe it.
- Maria: And this is supposed to bring bad luck.
There is a more or less logical explanation.
Well, it's not logical, but I've been investigating.
- Lucía: [laughs] Let's see.
- Maria: And apparently, when the sharpener passed by, there was a death.
Of course, people with super sharp knives, ready to use, well, sometimes
there was a death.
- Lucia: Every Sunday...
as a sport, after sharpening the knife [laughs].
- Maria: "What's on today?"
Stab".
Well, that's it, it's supposed to be like, "ah, if I put this on my head, they won't kill me."
or they're not going to kill anyone in my family."
I think that's where things might go.
But it is not known for sure.
It is a superstition that is not really known.
- Lucia: Wow.
- Maria: So...
How have I left you?
Have I left you...?
- Lucia: No, but without words.
You've left me speechless, absolutely.
It's just that I've also imagined...
I don't know, some ladies walking down the street and suddenly the sharpener passes by, who wouldn't have
what to put on your head and bag, bag on your head or something like that.
Or not either?
- Maria: No, no, I don't rule it out.
- Lucia: Oh, okay, okay.
- Maria: I've never seen it, I've never seen it, but I don't rule it out.
I think he's lost now...
- Lucia: How strong.
- Maria: I think he's lost because of that one, because now it's a recording...
Now it's not really that pan flute anymore (it used to be a real pan flute)...
Now, since it's a recording, I think it's lost its effect.
Oh well...
There will surely be people who continue doing it.
- Lucía: [laughs] I love it.
Excellent.
- Maria: Whenever I hear that, I remember my poor grandmother.
- Lucía: And I was thinking about basic things, like...
So, Maria, you were going to ask me about, I don't know, walking under a ladder,
see a black cat.
But this is great, this is beauty, this is pure beauty [laughs].
And it lasts, let's say, the most... culture
- Maria: Quality, quality.
- Lucia: Yes, quality.
Quality.
- Maria: Well yes, but we're going to leave it here, so that it doesn't take much longer for us.
long.
And of course, we have to say that we are going to make another video for your channel, that they have to go
to see it.
I'm going to leave the links in the description, in addition to the videos we already made.
a year...
I don't know when...
A while ago we made another video.
So...
- Lucía: Yes, it's been a while.
- Maria: Let's leave everything in the description section.
Am I forgetting something?
Or I think that would be all, right? That's what we have to remember, do you think?
Anything else?
- Lucía: Yes, we just talked about superstitions, well, that there are in Spain.
And we have to point out that Seville is a great city, despite what they say about Granada.
Seville exists apart from Granada.
And they make an important competition.
So, if you want to know why, know that now I am going to question you about it.
Sevilla.
- Maria: Ah.
That's right, exactly.
Now we are going to talk about Sevilla Vs Granada.
Let's see.
Well, nothing else then.
See you next time then, and thank you very much for being here, Lucía.
A place.
A big kiss to everyone and see you next time.
- Lucia: Thank you very much.
Thank you so much, Maria, for teaching me these things.
Bye bye.
A place.